<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- updated by Chris 01/21/21 -->

<!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.2.13 -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">

<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-yang-tls-tls13-sm-suites-06" number="8998" submissionType="independent" category="info" obsoletes="" updates="" xml:lang="en" tocInclude="true" sortRefs="true" symRefs="true" version="3">

  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.5.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="SM Cipher Suites for TLS 1.3">ShangMi (SM) Cipher Suites for TLS 1.3</title>
<!-- [rfced] Please note that the title of the document has been updated as
follows in order to more closely match use in past (similar) RFCs.


Original:

ShangMi (SM) Cipher Suites for Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.3

Current:
ShangMi (SM) Cipher Suites for TLS 1.3
-->

    
    <seriesInfo name="RFC" value="8998"/>
    <author initials="P." surname="Yang" fullname="Paul Yang">
      <organization>Ant Group</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>No. 77 Xueyuan Road</street>
          <city>Hangzhou</city>
          <code>310000</code>
          <country>China</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+86-571-2688-8888</phone>
        <email>kaishen.yy@antfin.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2021" month="March" />
    <area>Security</area>
    <workgroup>TLS</workgroup>

<!-- [rfced] Please insert any keywords (beyond those that appear in
the title) for use on https://www.rfc-editor.org/search. -->

<keyword>example</keyword>



    <abstract>
      <t>This document specifies how to use the ShangMi (SM) cryptographic
algorithms with Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol version 1.3.</t>
      <t>The use of these algorithms with TLS 1.3 is not endorsed by the
IETF.  The SM algorithms are becoming mandatory in China, so
this document provides a description of how to use the SM algorithms
with TLS 1.3 and specifies a profile of TLS 1.3 so that
implementers can produce interworking
implementations.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>This document describes two new cipher suites, a signature algorithm and a
key exchange mechanism for the Transport Layer
Security (TLS) protocol version 1.3 (TLS 1.3) (<xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/>).
These all utilize several ShangMi (SM) cryptographic algorithms
to fulfill the authentication and confidentiality requirements of TLS 1.3.
      The new cipher suites are as follows (see also <xref target="proposed" format="default"/>):</t>

      
      <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   CipherSuite TLS_SM4_GCM_SM3 = { 0x00, 0xC6 };
   CipherSuite TLS_SM4_CCM_SM3 = { 0x00, 0xC7 };
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>For a more detailed
introduction to SM cryptographic algorithms, please see <xref target="sm-algos" format="default"/>.
These cipher suites follow the TLS 1.3 requirements. Specifically,
all the cipher suites use SM4 in either Galois/Counter (GCM) mode
or Counter with CBC-MAC (CCM) mode to meet the needs of TLS 1.3 to have an encryption algorithm that is Authenticated Encryption with Associated Data (AEAD) capable.
The key exchange mechanism utilizes Elliptic Curve Diffie-Hellman
Ephemeral (ECDHE) over the SM2 elliptic curve, and the signature algorithm combines
the SM3 hash function and the SM2 elliptic curve signature scheme.</t>
      <t>For details about how these mechanisms negotiate shared encryption
keys, authenticate the peer(s), and protect the record structure, please see
<xref target="definitions" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>The cipher suites, signature algorithm, and key exchange mechanism
defined in this document are not recommended by the IETF. The SM
algorithms are becoming mandatory in China, so this document
provides a description of how to use them with TLS 1.3 and specifies
a profile of TLS 1.3 so that implementers can produce interworking
implementations.</t>
      <section anchor="sm-algos" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>The SM Algorithms</name>
        <t>Several different SM
cryptographic algorithms are used to integrate with TLS 1.3,
including SM2 for authentication, SM4 for
encryption, and SM3 as the hash function.</t>
<!-- [rfced] Does SM2 include multiple digital signatures, public key encryptions, and key exchange schemes?  (FYI - Note also the shift to remove awkward hyphenation of "elliptic curve based"; this was employed in at least one other place in the document.)

Original
SM2 is a set of elliptic curve based cryptographic algorithms including digital signature, public key encryption and key exchange scheme.

Perhaps A:
SM2 is a set of cryptographic algorithms based on elliptic curve cryptography, including digital signatures, public key encryptions, and key exchange schemes.

OR 

Perhaps B:
SM2 is a set of cryptographic algorithms based on elliptic curve cryptography, including a digital signature, public key encryption and key exchange scheme.
-->
        <t>SM2 is a set of elliptic-curve-based cryptographic algorithms, including digital
	signature, public key encryption and key exchange scheme.
<!--[rfced] Please review the time relationship conveyed in this text.

Original:
SM4 is a block cipher defined in [GBT.32907-2016] and now is being    
standardized by ISO to ISO/IEC 18033-3:2010 [ISO-SM4].

Perhaps:
SM4 is a block cipher defined in [GBT.32907-2016] and has been
standardized by ISO to ISO/IEC 18033-3:2010 [ISO-SM4].
-->

	In this document, only
the SM2 digital signature algorithm and basic key exchange scheme are involved, which have already been added
to ISO/IEC 14888-3:2018 <xref target="ISO-SM2" format="default"/> (as well as to <xref target="GBT.32918.2-2016" format="default"/>).
SM4 is a block cipher defined in <xref target="GBT.32907-2016" format="default"/> and now is being standardized
by ISO to ISO/IEC 18033-3:2010 <xref target="ISO-SM4" format="default"/>. SM3 is a hash function that produces an output of 256 bits. SM3 has already been accepted by ISO in
ISO/IEC 10118-3:2018 <xref target="ISO-SM3" format="default"/> and has also been described by <xref target="GBT.32905-2016" format="default"/>.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="term" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Terminology</name>
        <t>
    The key words "<bcp14>MUST</bcp14>", "<bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHALL
    NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14>", "<bcp14>SHOULD NOT</bcp14>", "<bcp14>RECOMMENDED</bcp14>", "<bcp14>NOT RECOMMENDED</bcp14>",
    "<bcp14>MAY</bcp14>", and "<bcp14>OPTIONAL</bcp14>" in this document are to be interpreted as
    described in BCP&nbsp;14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> 
    when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
        <t>Although this document is not an IETF Standards Track publication, it
adopts the conventions for normative language to provide clarity of
instruction to the implementer and to indicate requirement levels
for compliant TLS 1.3 implementations.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="proposed" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Algorithm Identifiers</name>
      <t>The cipher suites defined here have the following identifiers:</t>
      <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   CipherSuite TLS_SM4_GCM_SM3 = { 0x00, 0xC6 };
   CipherSuite TLS_SM4_CCM_SM3 = { 0x00, 0xC7 };
]]></sourcecode>
      <t>To accomplish a TLS 1.3 handshake, additional objects have been introduced along with
the cipher suites as follows:</t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The combination of the SM2 signature algorithm and SM3 hash function used in the Signature Algorithm
extension is defined in <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="of" section="B.3.1.3"/>:</li>
      </ul>
      <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
      SignatureScheme sm2sig_sm3 = { 0x0708 };
]]></sourcecode>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>The SM2 elliptic curve ID used in the Supported Groups extension is defined in <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="of" section="B.3.1.4"/>:</li>
      </ul>
      <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
      NamedGroup curveSM2 = { 41 };
]]></sourcecode>
    </section>
    <section anchor="definitions" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Algorithm Definitions</name>
      <section anchor="tls-versions" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>TLS Versions</name>
        <t>The new cipher suites defined in this document are only applicable to TLS 1.3.
Implementations of this document <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> apply these cipher suites to any older
versions of TLS.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="authentication" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Authentication</name>
        <section anchor="sm2-signature-scheme" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>SM2 Signature Scheme</name>
          <t>The Chinese government requires the use of the SM2 signature algorithm.
This section specifies the use of the SM2 signature algorithm
	  as the authentication method for a TLS 1.3 handshake.</t>
<!--[rfced] Should "algorithm" be added after "signature here?  FYI - This reference is behind a paywall.

Original:
 The SM2 signature is defined in [ISO-SM2].

Perhaps:
 The SM2 signature algorithm is defined in [ISO-SM2].
-->
	  
          <t>The SM2 signature is defined in <xref target="ISO-SM2" format="default"/>. The SM2 signature algorithm is
based on elliptic curves. The SM2 signature algorithm uses a fixed elliptic curve
parameter set defined in <xref target="GBT.32918.5-2016" format="default"/>. This curve is named "curveSM2" and has been assigned the value 41, as shown in <xref target="proposed" format="default"/>. Unlike other public key algorithms based on elliptic curve cryptography like the Elliptic Curve Digital Signature Algorithm (ECDSA), SM2 <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> select other elliptic curves.
But it is acceptable to write test cases that use other elliptic curve parameter
sets for SM2; see Annex F.14 of <xref target="ISO-SM2" format="default"/> as a reference.</t>
          <t>Implementations of the signature scheme and key exchange mechanism defined in this document <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to
what <xref target="GBT.32918.5-2016" format="default"/> requires; that is to say, the only valid elliptic curve
parameter set for the SM2 signature algorithm (a.k.a. curveSM2) is defined as follows:</t>
<dl><dt>curveSM2:</dt><dd>A prime field of 256 bits.</dd></dl>
<t>y<sup>2</sup> = x<sup>3</sup> + ax + b</t>
<sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   p  = FFFFFFFE FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF
        FFFFFFFF 00000000 FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF
   a  = FFFFFFFE FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF
        FFFFFFFF 00000000 FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFC
   b  = 28E9FA9E 9D9F5E34 4D5A9E4B CF6509A7
        F39789F5 15AB8F92 DDBCBD41 4D940E93
   n  = FFFFFFFE FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF FFFFFFFF
        7203DF6B 21C6052B 53BBF409 39D54123
   Gx = 32C4AE2C 1F198119 5F990446 6A39C994
        8FE30BBF F2660BE1 715A4589 334C74C7
   Gy = BC3736A2 F4F6779C 59BDCEE3 6B692153
        D0A9877C C62A4740 02DF32E5 2139F0A0
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>The SM2 signature algorithm requests an identifier value when generating or verifying
a signature. In all uses except when a client of a server needs to verify a peer's
SM2 certificate in the Certificate message, an implementation of this document
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the following ASCII string value as the SM2 identifier when doing a
TLS 1.3 key exchange:</t>
          <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   TLSv1.3+GM+Cipher+Suite
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>If either a client or a server needs to verify the peer's SM2 certificate
contained in the Certificate message, then the following ASCII string value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
used as the SM2 identifier according to <xref target="GMT.0009-2012" format="default"/>:</t>
          <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   1234567812345678
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>Expressed as octets, this is:</t>
          <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
   0x31, 0x32, 0x33, 0x34, 0x35, 0x36, 0x37, 0x38,
   0x31, 0x32, 0x33, 0x34, 0x35, 0x36, 0x37, 0x38
]]></sourcecode>
          <t>In practice, the SM2 identifier used in a certificate signature depends on the
certificate authority (CA) who signs that certificate. CAs may choose values other than the ones mentioned
above. Implementations of this document <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> confirm this information by themselves.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="kx" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Key Exchange</name>
        <section anchor="hello-messages" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Hello Messages</name>
          <t>The use of the algorithms defined by this document is negotiated during
the TLS handshake with information exchanged in the Hello messages.</t>
          <section anchor="clienthello" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>ClientHello</name>
            <t>To use the cipher suites defined by this document, a TLS 1.3 client includes
the new cipher suites in the "cipher_suites"
array of the ClientHello structure defined in <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="of" section="4.1.2"/>.</t>
            <t>Other requirements of this TLS 1.3 profile on the extensions of
ClientHello message are as follows:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>For the supported_groups extension, "curveSM2" <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included.</li>
              <li>For the signature_algorithms extension, "sm2sig_sm3" <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included.</li>
              <li>For the signature_algorithms_cert extension (if present), "sm2sig_sm3" <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included.</li>
              <li>For the key_share extension, a KeyShareEntry for the "curveSM2" group <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be included.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>
          <section anchor="serverhello" numbered="true" toc="default">
            <name>ServerHello</name>
            <t>If a TLS 1.3 server receives a ClientHello message containing the algorithms
defined in this document, it <bcp14>MAY</bcp14> choose to use them. If
so, then the server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> put one of the new cipher suites defined in this
document into its ServerHello's "cipher_suites" array and eventually send it
to the client side.</t>
            <t>A TLS 1.3 server's choice of what cipher suite to use depends on the configuration
of the server. For instance, a TLS 1.3 server may or not be configured to include the
new cipher suites defined in this document. Typical TLS 1.3
server applications also provide a mechanism that configures the cipher suite
preference on the server side. If a server is not configured to use the cipher suites
defined in this document, it <bcp14>SHOULD</bcp14> choose another cipher suite in the list that
the TLS 1.3 client provides; otherwise, the server <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> abort the handshake with
an "illegal_parameter" alert.</t>
<!-- [rfced] Since there is only one extension listed, should "extensions" be "extension"?

Original:
   The following extensions MUST conform to the new requirements:

Perhaps:
   The following extension MUST conform to the new requirements:
-->
            <t>The following extensions <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to the new requirements:</t>
            <ul spacing="normal">
              <li>For the key_share extension, a KeyShareEntry with SM2-related values <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be added
if the server wants to conform to this profile.</li>
            </ul>
          </section>
        </section>
        <section anchor="certificaterequest" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>CertificateRequest</name>
          <t>If a CertificateRequest message is sent by the server to require the client
to send its certificate for authentication purposes, for conformance to this
profile, the following is <bcp14>REQUIRED</bcp14>:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>The only valid signature algorithm present in "signature_algorithms" extension
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "sm2sig_sm3". That is to say, if the server chooses to conform to this profile,
the signature algorithm for the client's certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> use the SM2/SM3 procedure specified by this document.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="certificate" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>Certificate</name>
          <t>When a server sends the Certificate message containing the server certificate
to the client side, several new rules are added that will affect the certificate
selection:</t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>The public key in the certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be a valid SM2 public key.</li>
            <li>The signature algorithm used by the CA to sign the current certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
"sm2sig_sm3".</li>
            <li>The certificate <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be capable of signing; e.g., the digitalSignature bit
of X.509's Key Usage extension is set.</li>
          </ul>
        </section>
        <section anchor="certificateverify" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>CertificateVerify</name>
          <t>In the CertificateVerify message, the signature algorithm <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be "sm2sig_sm3",
indicating that the hash function <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be SM3 and the signature algorithm <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be
SM2.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section anchor="key-scheduling" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Key Scheduling</name>
        <t>As described in <xref target="sm-algos" format="default"/>, SM2 is actually a set of cryptographic
algorithms, including one key exchange protocol that defines methods such as
key derivation function, etc. This document does not define an SM2 key exchange
protocol, and an SM2 key exchange protocol <bcp14>SHALL NOT</bcp14> be used in the key exchange
steps defined in <xref target="kx" format="default"/>. Implementations of this document <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> always conform to
what TLS 1.3 <xref target="RFC8446" format="default"/> and its successors require regarding the key derivation and
related methods.</t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="cipher" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>Cipher</name>
        <t>The new cipher suites introduced in this document add two new AEAD encryption
algorithms, AEAD_SM4_GCM and AEAD_SM4_CCM, which stand for SM4 cipher in Galois/Counter
mode and SM4 cipher <xref target="GBT.32907-2016" format="default"/> in Counter with CBC-MAC mode, respectively.
The hash function for both cipher suites is SM3 (<xref target="ISO-SM3" format="default"/>).</t>
        <t>This section defines the AEAD_SM4_GCM and AEAD_SM4_CCM AEAD algorithms in a
style similar to what <xref target="RFC5116" format="default"/> used to define AEAD ciphers based on the AES cipher.</t>
        <section anchor="aeadsm4gcm" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>AEAD_SM4_GCM</name>
          <t>The AEAD_SM4_GCM authenticated encryption algorithm works as specified in <xref target="GCM" format="default"/>,
using SM4 as the block cipher, by providing the key, nonce, plaintext, and
associated data to that mode of operation. An authentication tag conforming to
the requirements of TLS 1.3 as specified in <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="of" section="5.2"/> <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be constructed using
the details in the TLS record header. The additional data input that forms the
authentication tag <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be the TLS record header. The AEAD_SM4_GCM ciphertext is formed by
appending the authentication tag provided as an output to the GCM encryption
operation to the ciphertext that is output by that operation. AEAD_SM4_GCM has 
four inputs: an SM4 key, an initialization vector (IV), a plaintext content, and optional 
additional authenticated data (AAD). AEAD_SM4_GCM generates two outputs: a ciphertext 
and message authentication code (also called an authentication tag). To have a common 
set of terms for AEAD_SM4_GCM and AEAD_SM4_CCM, the AEAD_SM4_GCM IV is referred to as a 
nonce in the remainder of this document. A simple test vector of AEAD_SM4_GCM and 
AEAD_SM4_CCM is given in <xref target="test-vectors"/> of this document.</t>
          <t>The nonce is generated by the party performing the authenticated encryption operation.
Within the scope of any authenticated encryption key, the nonce value <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> be unique.
That is, the set of nonce values used with any given key <bcp14>MUST NOT</bcp14> contain any duplicates.
Using the same nonce for two different messages encrypted with the same key
destroys the security properties of GCM mode. To generate the nonce, implementations of this document
<bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to TLS 1.3 (see <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.3"/>).</t>
          <t>The input and output lengths are as follows:</t>
          <ul empty="true">
<li>The SM4 key length is 16 octets.</li>
<li>The max plaintext length is 2<sup>36</sup> - 31 octets.</li>
<li>The max AAD length is 2<sup>61</sup> - 1 octets.</li>
<li>The nonce length is 12 octets.</li>
<li>The authentication tag length is 16 octets.</li>
<li>The max ciphertext length is 2<sup>36</sup> - 15 octets.</li>
</ul>
          <t>A security analysis of GCM is available in <xref target="MV04" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="aeadsm4ccm" numbered="true" toc="default">
          <name>AEAD_SM4_CCM</name>
          <t>The AEAD_SM4_CCM authenticated encryption algorithm works as specified in <xref target="CCM" format="default"/>
using SM4 as the block cipher. AEAD_SM4_CCM has four inputs: an SM4 key, a nonce,
a plaintext, and optional additional authenticated data (AAD). AEAD_SM4_CCM
generates two outputs: a ciphertext and a message authentication code (also called
an authentication tag). The formatting and counter generation functions are as
specified in Appendix A of <xref target="CCM" format="default"/>, and the values of the parameters
identified in that appendix are as follows:</t>
          <ul empty="true">
<li>The nonce length n is 12.</li>
<li>The tag length t is 16.</li>
<li>The value of q is 3.</li>
</ul>
          <t>An authentication tag is also used in AEAD_SM4_CCM. The generation of the authentication
tag <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to TLS 1.3 (See <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.2"/>).
The AEAD_SM4_CCM ciphertext is formed by appending the authentication tag provided
as an output to the CCM encryption operation to the ciphertext that is output
by that operation. The input and output lengths are as follows:</t>
<ul empty="true">
<li>   The SM4 key length is 16 octets.</li>
<li>   The max plaintext length is 2<sup>24</sup> - 1 octets.</li>
<li>   The max AAD length is 2<sup>64</sup> - 1 octets.</li>
<li>   The max ciphertext length is 2<sup>24</sup> + 15 octets.</li>
</ul>
          <t>To generate the nonce, implementations of this document <bcp14>MUST</bcp14> conform to
TLS 1.3 (see <xref target="RFC8446" sectionFormat="comma" section="5.3"/>).</t>
          <t>A security analysis of CCM is available in <xref target="J02" format="default"/>.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <t>IANA has assigned the values {0x00,0xC6} and {0x00,0xC7} with the names
"TLS_SM4_GCM_SM3" and "TLS_SM4_CCM_SM3"
to the "TLS Cipher Suites" registry with this document as reference:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Value</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
            <th align="left">DTLS-OK</th>
            <th align="left">Recommended</th>
            <th align="left">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="right">0x00,0xC6</td>
            <td align="left">TLS_SM4_GCM_SM3</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 8998</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="right">0x00,0xC7</td>
            <td align="left">TLS_SM4_CCM_SM3</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 8998</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>IANA has assigned the value 0x0708 with the name "sm2sig_sm3" to the
"TLS SignatureScheme" registry:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="right">Value</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
            <th align="left">Recommended</th>
            <th align="left">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="right">0x0708</td>
            <td align="left">sm2sig_sm3</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 8998</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>IANA has assigned the value 41 with the name "curveSM2" to the
"TLS Supported Groups" registry:</t>
      <table align="center">
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="right">Value</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
            <th align="left">DTLS-OK</th>
            <th align="left">Recommended</th>
            <th align="left">Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="right">41</td>
            <td align="left">curveSM2</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">No</td>
            <td align="left">RFC 8998</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>At the time of writing, there are no known weak keys for SM
cryptographic algorithms SM2, SM3 and SM4, and no security issues
have been found for these algorithms.</t>
      <t>A security analysis of GCM is available in <xref target="MV04" format="default"/>.</t>
      <t>A security analysis of CCM is available in <xref target="J02" format="default"/>.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5116.xml"/>



        <reference anchor="ISO-SM2" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/76382.html">
          <front>
            <title>IT Security techniques -- Digital signatures with appendix -- Part 3: Discrete logarithm based mechanisms</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2018" month="November"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="14888-3:2018"/>
        </reference>



        <reference anchor="ISO-SM3" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/67116.html">
          <front>
            <title>IT Security techniques -- Hash-functions -- Part 3: Dedicated hash-functions</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2018" month="October"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="10118-3:2018"/>
        </reference>



        <reference anchor="ISO-SM4" target="https://www.iso.org/standard/54531.html">
          <front>
            <title>Information technology -- Security techniques -- Encryption algorithms -- Part 3: Block ciphers</title>
            <author>
              <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2010" month="December"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="ISO/IEC" value="18033-3:2010"/>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="GCM" target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-38D/SP-800-38D.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation: Galois/Counter Mode (GCM) and GMAC</title>
            <author initials="M." surname="Dworkin">
              <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2007" month="November"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="Special Publication" value="800-38D"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.6028/NIST.SP.800-38D"/>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="CCM" target="http://csrc.nist.gov/publications/nistpubs/800-38C/SP800-38C.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Recommendation for Block Cipher Modes of Operation: the CCM Mode for Authentication and Confidentiality</title>
            <author initials="M." surname="Dworkin">
              <organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2004" month="May"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="Special Publication" value="800-38C"/>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.6028/NIST.SP.800-38C"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>



        <reference anchor="GBT.32907-2016" target="http://www.gmbz.org.cn/upload/2018-04-04/1522788048733065051.pdf">
         <front>
            <title>Information security technology -- SM4 block cipher algorithm</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Standardization Administration of the People's Republic of China</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="GB/T" value="32907-2016"/>
        </reference>



        <reference anchor="GBT.32905-2016" target="http://www.gmbz.org.cn/upload/2018-07-24/1532401392982079739.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Information security technology --- SM3 cryptographic hash algorithm</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Standardization Administration of China</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="GB/T" value="32905-2016"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="GBT.32918.2-2016" target="http://www.gmbz.org.cn/upload/2018-07-24/1532401673138056311.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Information security technology --- Public key cryptographic algorithm SM2 based on elliptic curves --- Part 2: Digital signature algorithm</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Standardization Administration of the People's Republic of China</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="GB/T" value="32918.2-2016"/>
        </reference>


<!-- [rfced] We were unable to find the date for this document. We also note that the date of this reference is 2017, while the serial number (GB/T 32918.5-2016) lists 2016. We did find GB/T 32918.5-2017 (https://www.chinesestandard.net/PDF.aspx/GBT32918.5-2017), where the date of issue is 08-29-2016 and the date of implementation is 03-01-2017. Please let us know if any updates are needed to this reference.
-->


        <reference anchor="GBT.32918.5-2016" target="http://www.gmbz.org.cn/upload/2018-07-24/1532401863206085511.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>Information security technology --- Public key cryptographic algorithm SM2 based on elliptic curves --- Part 5: Parameter definition</title>
            <author>
              <organization>Standardization Administration of the People's Republic of China</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2017" month="March"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="GB/T" value="32918.5-2016"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="GMT.0009-2012" target="http://www.gmbz.org.cn/main/viewfile/2018011001400692565.html">
          <front>
            <title>SM2 cryptography algorithm application specification</title>
            <author>
              <organization>State Cryptography Administration</organization>
            </author>
            <date year="2012" month="November"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="GM/T" value="0009-2012"/>
        </reference>



<!-- [rfced] Please note that the reference link provided (http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/ST/toolkit/BCM/documents/proposedmodes/ccm/ccm-ad1.pdf") for [J02] redirects to an article entitled "Block Cipher Techniques". Should the link in this reference be changed to "https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007%2F3-540-36492-7_7"?
-->


        <reference anchor="J02" target="http://csrc.nist.gov/groups/ST/toolkit/BCM/documents/proposedmodes/ccm/ccm-ad1.pdf">
          <front>
            <title>On the Security of CTR + CBC-MAC</title>
            <author initials="J." surname="Jonsson">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="February" year="2003"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/3-540-36492-7_7"/>
        </reference>


        <reference anchor="MV04" target="http://eprint.iacr.org/2004/193">
          <front>
            <title>The Security and Performance of the Galois/Counter Mode of Operation</title>
            <author initials="D." surname="McGrew">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <author initials="J." surname="Viega">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date year="2004" month="December"/>
          </front>
<seriesInfo name="DOI" value="10.1007/978-3-540-30556-9_27"/>
        </reference>
      </references>
    </references>
    <section anchor="test-vectors" numbered="true" toc="default">
      <name>Test Vectors</name>
      <t>All values are in hexadecimal and are in network byte order (big endian).</t>
      <section anchor="sm4-gcm-test-vectors" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SM4-GCM Test Vectors</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
Initialization Vector:   00001234567800000000ABCD
Key:                     0123456789ABCDEFFEDCBA9876543210
Plaintext:               AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABBBBBBBBBBBBBBBB
                         CCCCCCCCCCCCCCCCDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD
                         EEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF
                         EEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
Associated Data:         FEEDFACEDEADBEEFFEEDFACEDEADBEEFABADDAD2
CipherText:              17F399F08C67D5EE19D0DC9969C4BB7D
                         5FD46FD3756489069157B282BB200735
                         D82710CA5C22F0CCFA7CBF93D496AC15
                         A56834CBCF98C397B4024A2691233B8D
Authentication Tag:      83DE3541E4C2B58177E065A9BF7B62EC
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
      <section anchor="sm4-ccm-test-vectors" numbered="true" toc="default">
        <name>SM4-CCM Test Vectors</name>
        <sourcecode name="" type=""><![CDATA[
Initialization Vector:   00001234567800000000ABCD
Key:                     0123456789ABCDEFFEDCBA9876543210
Plaintext:               AAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABBBBBBBBBBBBBBBB
                         CCCCCCCCCCCCCCCCDDDDDDDDDDDDDDDD
                         EEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEFFFFFFFFFFFFFFFF
                         EEEEEEEEEEEEEEEEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA
Associated Data:         FEEDFACEDEADBEEFFEEDFACEDEADBEEFABADDAD2
CipherText:              48AF93501FA62ADBCD414CCE6034D895
                         DDA1BF8F132F042098661572E7483094
                         FD12E518CE062C98ACEE28D95DF4416B
                         ED31A2F04476C18BB40C84A74B97DC5B
Authentication Tag:      16842D4FA186F56AB33256971FA110F4
]]></sourcecode>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="contributors" numbered="false" toc="default">
      <name>Contributors</name>

    <contact fullname="Qin Long">
        <organization>Ant Group</organization>
        <address>
          <postal/>
          <email>zhuolong.lq@antfin.com</email>
        </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Kepeng Li">
        <organization>Ant Group</organization>
        <address>
          <postal/>
          <email>kepeng.lkp@antfin.com</email>
        </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Ke Zeng">
        <organization>Ant Group</organization>
        <address>
          <postal/>
          <email>william.zk@antfin.com</email>
        </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Han Xiao">
        <organization>Ant Group</organization>
        <address>
          <postal/>
          <email>han.xiao@antfin.com</email>
        </address>
    </contact>

    <contact fullname="Zhi Guan">
        <organization>Peking University</organization>
        <address>
          <postal/>
          <email>guan@pku.edu.cn</email>
        </address>
    </contact>
    </section>
<!-- [rfced] Throughout the text, note that we have used the format "TLS #" in lieu of "TLSv#" to match past use in similar RFCs.  We did not make this change in text marked as "sourcecode".

-->

    
  </back>
</rfc>
